Cruiser Houston Collection, 1917-2003
University of Houston Libraries
Cruiser Houston Collection
1917-2003
USS Houston Survivors Association; other donors
1981-001
68 boxes, 9 scrapbooks, 10 oversize items, 28 framed items, ship’s model; 48 linear feet
The heavy cruiser USS Houston (CA-30) was named for the city and port of Houston. On March 1, 1942, the Houston was sunk by the Japanese in Sunda Strait, and her surviving crew members were taken prisoner of war. The collection contains materials in a wide variety of formats that document the history of the ship and her crew.
Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries
Historical Note
On September 7, 1927, the U.S. Navy announced that in response to a local campaign, a new heavy cruiser would be named for the city of Houston. The ship’s keel was laid on May 1, 1928 at the Newport News Shipbuilding and Dry Dock Company. On September 7, 1929, the USS Houston (CA-30) was launched, and on June 17, 1930, she was commissioned.
In 1931, the Houston became flagship of the Asiatic Fleet. The Houston left the Asiatic in 1933 to join the Scouting Force, based in Long Beach, California. During the 1930s, avid fisherman President Franklin D. Roosevelt made four leisure cruises on the Houston. The Houston joined the Hawaiian Detachment in Pearl Harbor in November 1939, and returned to the Asiatic in March 1941.
On November 27, 1941, the USS Houston was undergoing some repairs at Cavite Naval Yard in the Philippine Islands when her captain, Albert H. Rooks, received a Navy Department warning about an impending Japanese attack on the Asiatic Fleet. The Houston was ordered to the central Philippines. On December 8, the crew learned of the outbreak of hostilities with Japan.
In January 1942 the Houston became part of a multi-national American-British-Dutch-Australian (ABDA) force. On February 4th, a group of ABDA ships attempted to intercept a Japanese force in the Makassar Straits, but were attacked by Japanese bombers. One of the bombs destroyed the Houston's rear 8-inch gun turret, killing 48 men and injuring 20 others.
On February 27, the Houston was among a fleet of ABDA ships that engaged a Japanese task force that was advancing on eastern Java. In the eight-hour Battle of the Java Sea, the Japanese inflicted defeat upon the ABDA ships, sinking or crippling two Dutch cruisers and three destroyers. Although the Houston was hit twice by Japanese 8" shells, she and the Australian light cruiser HMAS Perth both survived the battle.
On the night of February 28, the Houston and the Perth attempted to pass through Sunda Strait in an effort to reach the safer waters of the Indian Ocean. As they approached the entrance to the strait, they unexpectedly encountered a Japanese force that was protecting the invasion fleet. In the ensuing battle, four torpedoes struck and sunk the Perth. The Houston managed to hit three destroyers and sink a minesweeper, but was struck by four torpedoes and started to sink. Following orders to abandon ship, crew members jumped over the sides and began to swim for the distant shore of Java. The Battle of Sunda Strait and the sinking of the ship took the lives of 700 of the Houston's 1068 crew members.
When news of the ship’s sinking reached Houstonians, they raised money to build the light cruiser USS Houston (CL-81), as well as a small aircraft carrier. On Memorial Day, 1942, one thousand “Houston Volunteers” were sworn into the Navy to symbolically replace the Houston's crew, who were all presumed dead.
In Java or its surrounding waters, the Houston crew members who survived the sinking were taken prisoner by the Japanese. They were marched to the town of Serang and held there until April 1942, when most of the men were transported to "Bicycle Camp" in Batavia. There the men of the Houston were joined by troops from the 2nd Battalion, 131st Field Artillery, a National Guard unit from Texas (nicknamed the “Lost Battalion”).
In October, the majority of the POWs were taken to Moulmein, Burma, while the rest were sent to work in various camps throughout Asia. There they became slave labor for a Japanese project to build a railroad for transporting troops and supplies from Thailand to Burma. Sixty-one thousand Allied prisoners-of-war and over 200,000 Asian natives worked on the Burma-Thai Railway, which eventually stretched 250 miles between mountains, across rivers, and through jungles. The men were fed starvation rations, beaten frequently, and subject to illnesses such as beri beri, pellagra, malaria, and tropical ulcers.
Nearly 13,000 Allied POWs and 100,000 Asian natives died building the “Death Railway,” including 79 men from the Houston. Upon the railway's completion in October 1943, the surviving POWs were scattered to various camps in Singapore, Burma, Indochina, and Japan. On August 16, 1945, the POWs learned that the war was over and they were to return home.
Following the war, survivor Otto Schwarz formed the USS Houston Survivors Association, whose newsletter was named the Blue Bonnet after the original ship's newsletter. Many survivors kept in touch by attending annual reunions with their friends from the Lost Battalion. In 1981, the survivors donated a collection of archival materials and memorabilia to the UH Libraries, which built a Cruiser Houston Memorial Room to display the items. On March 21, 1981, they celebrated the launch of another ship named “Houston,” the nuclear powered submarine USS Houston (SSN-713). And in 1995, the Texas Commandery of the Naval Order of the United States dedicated a monument to the USS Houston and her crew in downtown Houston.
In 1991 the Survivors Association formed a complementary group called the Next Generation, made up of children and younger relatives of survivors. Under the direction of Next Generation members Val Roberts-Poss and Lin Drees, and co-editor Otto Schwarz, the Blue Bonnet continues to come out four times a year. Roberts-Poss and Drees also organize an annual memorial service in Houston at the site of the downtown monument.
Chronology
January 1, 1927 First meeting of the Cruiser Houston Committee
September 7, 1927 Navy announces that heavy cruiser will be named for Houston
May 1, 1928 Ships keel laid at Newport News Shipbuilding and Dry Dock Company
September 7, 1929 USS Houston (CA-30) launched in Newport News, Virginia
June 17, 1930 Ship commissioned in the United States Navy Yard
February 22, 1931 Houston becomes flagship ofAsiatic Fleet
1933 Houston joins Scouting Force based in Long Beach, CA
July 1, 1934 First cruise by President Franklin D. Roosevelt
Oct. 3, 1935 Second Presidential Cruise
July 16, 1938 Third Presidential Cruise
February 18, 1939 Fourth Presidential Cruise
November 7, 1939 Houston in Pearl Harbor with Hawaiian Detachment
November 27, 1941 Houston ordered to central Philippines
January 15, 1942 Houston becomes part of American-British-Dutch-Australian (ABDA) force
February 4, 1942 Battle of Makassar Strait
February 27, 1942 Battle of the Java Sea
February 28-March 1, 1942 Battle of Sunda Strait and sinking of USS Houston (CA-30)
March 1942 USS Houston crew members become POWs
May 30, 1942 Thousand Houston Volunteers join Navy
June 19, 1943 USS Houston (CL-81) launched
October 1942- October 1943 Burma-Thai Railway built with POW labor
August 16, 1945 Houston crew members learn war is over
1948 Beginnings of USS Houston Survivors Association
March 21, 1981 USS Houston (SSN-713) launched
November 11, 1995 USS Houston monument dedicated
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of materials in a wide variety of formats that document the history of the USS Houston (CA-30) and her crew. A significant portion of the material dates from the period 1929 to 1945. There is also a large quantity of material that dates from the 1980s to the present.
The materials have been divided into four major categories:
• Core Material is the material most frequently requested by researchers, and includes Photographs, Negatives and Slides, Correspondence, Diaries, Blue Bonnets, Deck Logs, Reports, Statements, Rosters, and POW Camp Records.
• Printed Material includes Citations, Certificates, Programs, Booklets and Pamphlets, Documents, Newsletters, Articles, and Clippings.
• Literary Productions include Personal Accounts, Typescripts/Historical Accounts, Oral Histories, Commemorative Booklets, Poetry, and Speeches.
• Other Material includes primarily material in formats other than papers or photographs, such as Scrapbooks, Invitations, Menus, Memorabilia, Film and Video Recordings, Audio Recordings, Maps and Ships’ Plans, Miscellaneous Artworks, Framed Items, and Plaques.
Books and commercial videotapes have been removed from the collection and incorporated into the library’s cataloged holdings. These may be found by searching the UH Libraries’ catalog by author, using the phrase “Cruiser Houston Collection.”
Additional materials related to the history of the USS Houston (CA-30) and her crew may be found in the William A. Bernrieder Collection. A permanent exhibit of materials from the Cruiser Houston Collection is on display in the M.D. Anderson Library of the University of Houston. The UH Libraries also maintains a digital exhibit on the USS Houston (CA-30) online at http://info.lib.uh.edu/sca/digital/cruiser/cruiserh.htm.
Subjects (Persons)
Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945
Subjects
Houston (Cruiser: CA-30).; Java Sea, Battle of the (Indonesia), 1942; Sunda Strait, Battle of, Indonesia, 1942; Burma-Siam Railroad.; World War, 1939-1945 -- Prisoners and prisons, Japanese.
Formats
Diaries; Letters (correspondence); Memorabilia; Negatives; Newsletters; Photographs; Paintings; Postcards; Reminiscences; Reports; Rosters; Scrapbooks; Videocassettes
Acquisition Information
The original core of material that makes up this collection was donated to the UH Libraries by members of the USS Houston Survivors Association in 1981. Additional donations from crew members of the USS Houston (CA-30), their family members, and other individuals have been made steadily since the initial donation.
Access Restrictions
Open for research.
Detailed Description of the Collection
- PHOTOGRAPHS, 1917-2003
  This series contains black & white and color photographic prints, including some oversize and panoramic prints. The photographs are arranged into sub-series by general subject. Within each sub-series, the photographs are in alphabetical order according to the subjects of the individual photograph. Some of the photographs are copies of prints from institutions such as the National Archives or the U.S. Naval Institute.
  Box 4 includes a binder of photographs taken by a professional photographer at the 2002 USS Houston Survivors Association Reunion. If reproduced in print or on a website, or otherwise publicly displayed, these photographs must include the following credit line: Copyright Arturo Sanchez, Frank White Photography.
  - Bell, Ship’s
    - Bell, 1973., Donor: William A. Bernrieder (Box 54, Folder 9)
    - Bell, 1981. (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Donor: Otto Schwarz
    - Bell, undated. (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Donor: Betty Batchelor Miles
  - (George R.) Brown Room Opening
    - William A. Bernrieder, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - William A. Bernrieder and Admiral Hayward Brown, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Admiral Hayward Brown, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Brown Room exhibit, 1981. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Brown Room opening, 1981. (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Donor: Harold R. Rooks
    - Brown Room opening, 1981. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Brown Room opening, 1981. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Brown Room opening, 1981. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Brown Room opening, 1981. (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Brown Room opening, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Brown Room sign, 1981. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Brown Room speakers, 1981. (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Contact sheets, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Barry Munitz, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Captain Albert H. Rooks Medals, 1981. (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Harold Rooks, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Crew Members (Group Shots)
    - Chiefs, 1932. (Box 1, Folder 19)
      Donor: Philip Wayne and Sean Ellerbee
    - Crew in China, [1932?]. (Box 1, Folder 20)
      Donor: Norrie C. Gardiner
    - Crew [in Japan?], [1930s] (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Crew, Pearl Harbor, Hawaiian Territory, [ca. 1941]. (Box 54, Folder 1)
      Donor: John Stefanek
    - Crew, panoramic photograph, 1934 (Ovs OVS, Pan PAN)
    - Crew, [1930s]. (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Crew members, 1938 and 1939 (Box 1, Folder 23)
      Donor: Everett L. Malone
    - Crew members, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
      Donor: Harold J. “Hap” Heidel
    - Crew members, USS Houston and USS Kent, Manila, P.I., 1933. (Box 1, Folder 25)
      Donors: Phillip Wayne and Sean Ellerbee
    - F Division, Manila, P.I., 1941. (Box 1, Folder 26)
      Donor: Henry P. Thew
    - Marine Detachment, 1932. (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Officers, 1936. (Box 1, Folder 28)
      Donor: Story Sloane
  - USS Houston (AK-1)
    - USS Houston (AK 1), [copy prints, U.S. Naval Historical Center], 1917-1918 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - USS Houston (AK 1), undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
      Donor: William A. Bernrieder
    - Werdenfels, undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - USS Houston (CA-30)
    - Design model, Navy Department, [1920s]. (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Naming campaign, 1927. (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Name announcement, 1927. (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Christening party at White House, 1929 (Ovs OVS, Pan PAN)
    - Christening party at White House, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Launching ceremony, 1929. (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Launching ceremony, 1929. (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Launching ceremony, 1929. (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Launching ceremony, 1929. (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Launching ceremony, 1929. (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Launching ceremony, 1929. (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Launching ceremony, 1929. (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Launching ceremony, 1929. (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Ship Channel Cruise [removed from album page], 1936 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - USS Houston (CA-30) after refit, 1939-1940. (Box 1, Folder 45)
      Donor: Ned Gallagher
    - USS Houston (CA 30), through gun site, [1942?]. (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - USS Houston (CA 30) under Brooklyn Bridge, undated (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - USS Houston in Caribbean, 1939. (Box 54, Folder 10)
    - USS Houston (CA-30) in China, undated (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - USS Houston (CA-30) in Honolulu Harbor, [copy print, U.S. Naval Institute], 1933 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - USS Houston (CA-30) arrives at Honolulu, Presidential Cruise, [copy print, U.S. Naval Institute], 1934 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - USS Houston (CA-30), Honolulu, Presidential Cruise, 1934 (Ovs OVS, Pan PAN)
    - USS Houston (CA-30) in Houston, 1936. (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - USS Houston (CA-30) in Houston Ship Channel, [ca. 1930s] (Box 1, Folder 52)
    - USS Houston (CA-30) in Houston Ship Channel, [ca. 1930s] (Box 1, Folder 53)
    - USS Houston (CA 30) in dry dock in Manila, P.I., [copy print, U.S. Naval Institute], 1939 (Box 1, Folder 54)
    - USS Houston (CA-30) in Manila Bay, P.I., [1931?]. (Box 1, Folder 55)
    - USS Houston (CA-30) in Manila Bay, P.I. 1940. (Box 1, Folder 56)
    - USS Houston (CA-30) in Manila Bay, P.I., 1941. (Box 1, Folder 57)
    - USS Houston (CA-30) in San Diego, Presidential Cruise, 1932. (Box 1, Folder 58)
    - USS Houston (CA-30) off San Diego, Presidential Cruise, [copy print, U.S. Naval Historical Center], 1935 (Box 1, Folder 59)
    - USS Houston (CA-30) leaves San Diego, Presidential Cruise, [copy print, U.S. Naval Institute], 1935 (Box 1, Folder 60)
    - USS Houston (CA 30) and San Jacinto Monument, 1939. (Box 1, Folder 61)
    - USS Houston (CA-30) in San Francisco [copy print, U.S. Naval Institute], 1937 (Box 1, Folder 62)
    - USS Houston (CA-30) in San Francisco Bay [newspaper clipping], 1934 (Box 1, Folder 63)
    - USS Houston (CA-30) at sea, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 64)
      Donor: Jack L. Williams
    - USS Houston (CA-30) at Shanghai, deck with airplanes, [copy print, U.S. Naval Institute], undated (Box 1, Folder 65)
    - USS Houston (CA-30) at Shanghai, [copy print, U.S. Naval Institute], undated (Box 1, Folder 66)
    - USS Houston (CA-30) [in Shanghai?], [copy print, U.S. Naval Institute], 1930's (Box 1, Folder 67)
    - USS Houston (CA-30) in Ship Channel, 1930. (Box 1, Folder 68)
    - USS Houston (CA-30) in Ship Channel, [copy print, U.S. Naval Historical Center], 1930 (Box 1, Folder 69)
    - USS Houston (CA-30) at Tjilatjap, 1942. (Box 1, Folder 70)
    - USS Houston (CA-30) in Wangpoo [Huangpu] River, Shanghai, 1930's (Box 1, Folder 71)
    - USS Houston (CA 30) and USS Peary, Darwin, Australia, 1942. (Box 1, Folder 72)
    - USS Houston (CA 30), [ca.1931-1936]. (Box 1, Folder 73)
    - USS Houston (CA-30), 1935. (Box 1, Folder 74)
      Donor: Phillip Wayne and Sean Ellerbee
    - USS Houston (CA 30), 1939. (Box 1, Folder 75)
    - USS Houston (CA 30), 1939. (Box 1, Folder 76)
    - USS Houston (CA 30) [copy print, U.S. Naval Institute], 1940 (Box 1, Folder 77)
    - USS Houston (CA 30), 1941. (Box 1, Folder 78)
      Donor: USS Houston Survivors Association
    - Houston (CA 30), undated (Box 1, Folder 79)
    - USS Houston (CA 30), undated (Box 54, Folder 3)
    - USS Houston (CA 30), undated (Box 54, Folder 4)
    - USS Houston (CA 30), undated (Box 1, Folder 80)
    - USS Houston (CA-30), undated (Box 1, Folder 81)
    - USS Houston (CA 30), [copy print, U.S. Naval Historical Center], undated (Box 1, Folder 82)
    - USS Houston (CA 30), [copy prints, U.S. Naval Institute], undated (Box 1, Folder 83)
    - USS Houston (CA 30), undated. (Box 1, Folder 84)
    - USS Houston (CA-30), undated. (Box 1, Folder 85)
    - USS Houston (CA-30), undated. (Box 1, Folder 86)
  - USS Houston (CL-81)
    - Mrs. Claude B. Hamill, launching ceremony, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Launching ceremony, 1943. (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Launching ceremony, 1943. (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Launching ceremony, [copy print, National Archives], 1943 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - USS Houston (CL-81), [copy print, National Archives], 1944 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - USS Houston (CL-81), [copy print, National Archives], 1944 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - USS Houston (CL 81) in Ship Channel, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - USS Houston (SSN-713)
    - Barbara Bush, launching ceremony, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - George Bush, launching ceremony, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Launching ceremony, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - USS Houston (SSN-713), undated. (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - USS Houston (CA-30) Survivors Association
    - Houston and Lost Battalion Survivors, 1956. (Box 2, Folder 12)
      Donor: Doris Smith
    - USS Houston Survivors Association, group photo, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - USS Houston Survivors Association Reunion, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - USS Houston Survivors Association Reunion, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - USS Houston Survivors Association Reunion, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - USS Houston Survivors Association Reunion, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - USS Houston Survivors Association reunion, 1985. (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - USS Houston Survivors Association reunion, 1985. (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - USS Houston Survivors Association reunion, 1985. (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - USS Houston Survivors Association reunion, 1985. (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - USS Houston Survivors Association reunion, 1985. (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - USS Houston Survivors Association reunion, 1985. (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - USS Houston Survivors Association reunion, 1985. (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - USS Houston Survivors Association reunion, 1999. (Box 2, Folder 25)
      Donor: Phillip Wayne Ellerbee
    - USS Houston Survivors Association reunion, (copyright Arturo Sanchez, Frank White Photography), 2002 (Box 2, Binder Binder)
  - Houston Volunteers
    - Rear Admiral William A. Glassford, 1942. (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Houston Volunteers, 1942. (Box 2, Folder 27)
      Donor: Doris Allen, in memory of Wm. E. Allen, Sr.
    - Houston Volunteers, 1942. (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Individuals
    - William Baggaley, 1936. (Box 54, Folder 5)
    - Guy Baker, undated. (Box 54, Folder 6)
    - Thomas F. Ball, undated. (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - George N. Barker, undated (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - William C. Batchelor, Jr., undated. (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - William A. Bernrieder and Marvin Robinson, photocopy, 1993. (Box 2, Folder 32)
      Donor: Carter B. Conlin
    - Mary Ellen Bute and Elisabeth Holcombe, 1929. (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Harry F. Byrd, 1929. (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Captain, undated (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Cardinellie, 1939. (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Francis Cogswell, 1939. (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - R.A Dawes, undated. (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - William Martin DeShields, undated. (Box 2, Folder 39)
      Donor: Donald F. DeShields
    - George E. Detre, 1945. (Box 2, Folder 40)
      Donor: George E. Detre
    - Sean Ellerbee, 1999. (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Sean Ellerbee, 1999. (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Frank D. Ellis, ca. 1941. (Box 2, Folder 43)
      Donor: Dominick DiMassimo
    - Mr. and Mrs. Frank D. Ellis; F.G. Polk, 1941. (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - W.O. Frederick, 1939. (Box 2, Folder 45)
      Donors: Gary E. and Gregory P. White
    - Jesse B. Gay, undated. (Box 54, Folder 11)
    - C.B. Gillespie, undated (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Admiral Thomas Hart, 1941. (Box 2, Folder 47)
      Donor: Robert Pistole
    - Gilbert W. Hayes, [ca. 1938]. (Box 2, Folder 48)
      Donor: Gilbert W. Hayes
    - Hollingsworth, John William “Bill” and his brother Clarence Solomon Turner, photocopies, undated. (Box 2, Folder 49)
      Donor: Irene Mills
    - Edwin F. Hoofer, ca. 1939. (Box 2, Folder 50)
      Donor: Pam Crispi Foster
    - Edwin F. Hoofer, ca. 1939. (Box 54, Folder 12)
    - Farrel W. Keith, [ca. 1942] (Box 2, Folder 51)
      (printed digital copy).
      Donor: Clyde Keith
    - A.G. Kirchner, [ca. 1930s] (Box 2, Folder 52)
      (printed digital copies).
      Donor: Bob Kirchner
    - Lawrence F. Kondzela, [ca. 1940s] (Box 2, Folder 53)
      Donor: Susan Pogue
    - Capt. George Mensch and Liz Wachendorfer, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - Capt. George Mensch and Liz Wachendorfer, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 55)
    - Capt. George Mensch and Liz Wachendorfer, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 56)
    - Capt. George Mensch and Liz Wachendorfer, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 57)
    - Dan Moody, undated. (Box 2, Folder 58)
    - William Dow Newton, undated (Box 2, Folder 59)
      Donor: Mrs. C.L. Abrahamson
    - Nickel, Henry, ca. 1930s and 1947. (Box 2, Folder 60)
    - Jesse B. Oldendorf, 1940. (Box 54, Folder 7)
    - [Lennart O.] Peterson, 1938. (Box 2, Folder 61)
    - Lester W. Rehfeld, 1941. (Box 2, Folder 62)
    - Lester W. Rehfeld, undated. (Box 2, Folder 63)
    - Capt. Albert H. Rooks, 1941. (Box 2, Folder 64)
    - Capt. Albert H. Rooks, 1941. (Box 2, Folder 65)
    - Capt. Albert H. Rooks, undated. (Box 2, Folder 66)
    - Franklin D. Roosevelt, 1935. (Box 2, Folder 67)
      Donor: John C. Reas
    - Franklin D. Roosevelt, ca. 1930's. (Box 2, Folder 68)
      (in exhibit?)
    - Franklin D. Roosevelt, ca. 1930's (Box 2, Folder 69)
    - Franklin D. Roosevelt, ca. 1930's (Box 2, Folder 70)
    - Franklin D. Roosevelt and party aboard Houston, [copy print, U.S. Naval Academy Library], ca. 1930's (Box 2, Folder 71)
    - Henry L. Roosevelt, 1935. (Box 2, Folder 72)
    - Henry L. Roosevelt, undated (Box 2, Folder 73)
    - R.E. Saunders and other crew members, undated. (Box 2, Folder 74)
      Donor: Owen Saunders
    - A.D. Simpson, undated. (Box 2, Folder 75)
    - Jack Smith with American flag, undated (Box 2, Folder 76)
    - Jack and June Smith, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 77)
    - John Stefanek and Suho Suomi, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 78)
    - Claude A. Swanson, undated. (Box 54, Folder 8)
    - Curtis D. Wilbur, undated. (Box 2, Folder 79)